hey what's up guys my name is Aero and
welcome back to my C++ series last time
we talked about Constructors in C++ and
what they are and how to use them
definitely check out that video if you
haven't already and today we're going to
talk about their evil twin the
destructor so similarly how a
Constructor runs when you create a new
instance of an object a Destructor runs
when you destroy an object so anytime an
object gets destroyed the destructor
method will get called The Constructor
is usually where you set variables up or
do any kind of initialization that you
need to do and similarly the destructor
is where you unin ize anything that you
might have to or clean any memory that
you've used the destructure applies to
both stack and Heap allocated objects so
if you allocate an object using new when
you call delete the destructor will get
called if you just have a stack based
object then when the scope ends the
object will get deleted and thus the
destructor will get called let's dive in
and take a look at some examples so in
the Constructor video we created this
wonderful entity class which had
multiple Constructors here let's go
ahead and add a Destructor a Destructor
begins with a tier and then the name of
our class so basically the only
difference between a construct and a
Destructor in terms of Declaration and
definition is the actual tier that you
put at the front of the destructor
that's how you know it's a Destructor in
this case we just have a simple class
with two members X and Y there is
absolutely no clean up we need to do for
memory here at all since these two
floats are allocated in place with our
class we're going to talk way more about
memory allocation and all of that
complicated stuff in the future so don't
you worry but for an example let's go
ahead and add a message which tells us
that the object has been deleted so I
might write something like destroyed
entity and then for fun in our
Constructor here I'm going to write
constructed
entity or I guess we should call it
created since we called this destroyed
and not destructed I'm going to get rid
of this Constructor just so we don't get
too confused I'll initialize X and Y to
Z as well just so that we're not crazy
I'll get rid of this as well now since
this is stack allocated we will only see
the destructure getting called when the
main function exits which we're not
really going to see because our program
will close immediately after that so I'm
going to just write a function here
which will perform all of our entity
operations I'll move all this code over
here and I will call function now if I
run my code just like this you should
see created entity then our print
function running which prints X and Y
and then finally destroyed entity let's
take a deeper look as to how this works
I'm going to put a break point on line
28 here next to our entity and hit F5
currently I've got absolutely nothing in
the console if I hit F10 here and look
back you can see that my entity has been
created I'm then going to hit F10 to
print and you can see that my X and Y
position gets printed and then finally
the end of the scope is reached here
we're about to jump back to line 34
which is our return address since this
object was created on the stack it
should get automatically destroyed when
it goes out of scope which is right over
here so if I hit F10 you can see that
destroyed entity gets printed to the
console because the destructor is called
we jump back to our return address and
everything is good so that is
essentially what a Destructor is it's
just a special function a special method
which gets called when an object gets
destroyed as for some real world
examples as to why you would ever write
a instructor well again if there is
certain initialization code that you've
called in the Constructor you will
likely want to uninitialize or destroy
all of that stuff in the destructor
because if you don't you can get memory
licks a good example of that is Heap
allocated objects if you've allocated
any kind of memory on the Heap manually
then you need to manually clean it up if
it was allocated throughout the usage of
the entity or in the entity Constructor
you're likely going to want to get rid
of it in the destructor because when the
destructor gets called that entity is
gone you can also call the destructor
manually not something that I see a lot
of people doing rightly so it's a bit
weird if you end up doing something like
that the only reason I can really think
of doing that is maybe if you've
allocated using new however when you
delete it you decide to use something
like the free function and then you also
want to call the destructor manually in
that case I don't know not really use
that often but you can do so by just
calling e do entity like this as if it
was any other function and that will
actually call it instructor if I run
this
code which is innocent enough you can
see that it destroys the entity twice
seemingly we're not actually releasing
any resources here so it doesn't crash
it just prints this message twice again
not something I would recommend or not
something I I see often at all very very
rarely I've seen something like this so
yeah destructors sorted I'll see you
guys next time goodbye you
[Music]